Guide to the University of Pittsburgh, Board of Trustees, Meeting Minutes, 1845-present UA.1.4
ULS Archives & Special Collections
University of Pittsburgh, Board of Trustees, Meeting Minutes
1845-present
ULS Archives & Special Collections
University of Pittsburgh. Board of Trustees
University of Pittsburgh. Secretary
Western University of Pennsylvania
UA.1.4
3.8 Linear Feet (9 boxes)
This collection contains the meeting minutes of the Board of Trustees of the Western University of Pennsylvania from April 1845 to June 1908 and its successor, the University of Pittsburgh, from July 1908 to the present.
Access Restrictions
Based on the provisions of the September 12, 1974, Pennsylvania Sunshine Act, meetings of the Board of Trustees were designated as either "public" or "information" meetings. While minutes of public Board and committee meetings may be accessed by researchers immediately, minutes of information meetings are closed to researchers for a period of twenty-five years per the University's "Policy on Access to the Board of Trustees Files" signed by Chancellor Wesley W. Posvar on July 25, 1980.
Previous Citation
University of Pittsburgh, Board of Trustees, Meeting Minutes, 1845-present, UA.1.4, University of Pittsburgh Archives
History
On February 28, 1787, the Pennsylvania Assembly approved an act creating the Pittsburgh Academy, which stipulated that the school's Board of Trustees would include "twenty-one members, seven of whom shall be a board or quorum to transact all the business of the said Academy." The newly established school's trustees included several prominent members of the community, including Col. Presley Neville and Nathaniel Bedford.
On February 18, 1819, the Commonwealth approved another act incorporating the Western University of Pennsylvania (WUP), citing the desire of the trustees of the Pittsburgh Academy to found a university in Pittsburgh. This act stipulated that the Trustees of WUP should consist of "twenty-six Trustees, nine of whom shall form a quorum or board." George Stevenson of Pittsburgh was elected to serve as the first President of the Board of Trustees of the University. Because several of the trustees were unable to attend meetings of the Board, an Act of Assembly was issued on March 9, 1826, to convene a new Board of Trustees. A March 6, 1872, supplement to the act of incorporation expanded the Board of Trustees to thirty-three members and included the mayors of Pittsburgh and Allegheny, as well as the Chancellor of the University. This supplement also stated that the Board would annually elect a president, treasurer, and secretary, the latter of which could not be a trustee. In addition, it established an Executive Committee consisting of the President and six additional annually elected trustees to act while the Board was not in session.
At the request of the Board of Trustees, the Western University of Pennsylvania changed its name to the University of Pittsburgh in 1908. In 1949, the Executive Committee of the Board of Trustees was expanded to nine total members. In March 1960, the membership of the Board was amended to consist of: twelve Charter Trustees, at least one of which had to be an alumnus; nine Alumni Trustees that served three year terms with the ability to serve one succeeding consecutive term; nine Term Trustees that served three year terms with the ability to serve one succeeding consecutive term; and two ex officio members, the Mayor of Pittsburgh and the Chancellor of the University. At age seventy-two, a trustee could be elected as an Emeritus Trustee for life. Also at this time, the Executive Committee was expanded to nine elected members and the Chairman.
In September 1966, the Board of Trustees approved changes to the University's by-laws to make it a state-related school. Additionally, the composition of the Board was changed to include twenty-four University Trustees, including eleven Charter Trustees, six Term Trustees, and 6 Alumni Trustees. The Chancellor was appointed as one of the University Trustees. Also included were twelve Commonwealth Trustees, of which the Governor of Pennsylvania, President pro-tempore of the State Senate, and Speaker of the State house each appoint four individuals. The Governor, Mayor of Pittsburgh, and the State Superintendent of Public Instruction were made ex officio members.
On September 12, 1974, Pennsylvania's Open Meetings Law, often referred to as the Sunshine Act, stipulated that meetings of the Board of Trustees would be open to the public and that minutes of the meetings would be made available for public review. In order to conduct confidential business, the Board could convene information meetings, which were not open to the public. In 1987, an amendment to the Sunshine Act stated that public committee meeting minutes were also made available to the public.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in chronological order.
Acquisition Information
Minutes are periodically transferred to the University Archives from the Office of the Board of Trustees Secretery.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection contains the meeting minutes of the Board of Trustees of the Western University of Pennsylvania from April 1845 to June 1908 and its successor, the University of Pittsburgh, from July 1908 to the present. [Note: this finding aid only currently provides access to historic minutes from 1845-1945.]
Minutes of Board of Trustees meetings held prior to April 1845 were destroyed by a fire. Also, while the minutes in this collection may include reports from Board of Trustees committees, such as the Executive and Facilities Committees, the minutes of committee meetings are not present.
In addition to meeting minutes, this collection also includes supporting documentation that is referenced during meetings. This may include correspondence, treasurer reports, and lists of students confirmed by the Board for graduation, among others.
Universities and colleges -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Administration; Universities and colleges -- Pennsylvania; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- History; University of Pittsburgh; Universities and colleges -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Records and correspondence; Universities and colleges -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- History; University of Pittsburgh; University of Pittsburgh. Board of Trustees; Western University of Pennsylvania
- Blank Pages from Volume 1, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Western University of Pennsylvania, Board of Trustees Special Meeting Minutes, April 14 and April 29, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, April 14, 1845; 1.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, April 29, 1845; 2.
- Western University of Pennsylvania, Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, May 1845-August 1845 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, May 8, 1845; 1.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, June 4, 1845; 2.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, June 10, 1845; 3.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Adjourned Meeting of the Board of Trustees, June 12, 1845; 4.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Adjourned Meeting of the Board of Trustees, June 17, 1845; 5.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Adjourned Meeting of the Board of Trustees, June 24, 1845; 6.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, July 10, 1845; 7.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, July 15, 1845; 8.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, July 17, 1845; 9.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, August 5, 1845; 10.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, August 29, 1845; 11.
- Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, January 6, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, January 20, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Western University of Pennsylvania, Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, June 1846-March 1847 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, June 2, 1846; 1.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, June 25, 1846; 2.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, August 18, 1846; 3.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, September 3, 1846; 4.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, September 8, 1846; 5.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, September 29, 1846; 6.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, October 21, 1846; 7.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, November 18, 1846; 8.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, January 4, 1847; 9.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, March 2, 1847; 10.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, March 30, 1847; 11.
- Western University of Pennsylvania, Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, April 13 and June 8, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, April 13, 1847; 1.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, June 8, 1847; 2.
- Western University of Pennsylvania, Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, September 1847-February 1854 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, September 9, 1847; 1.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, November 22, 1847; 2.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, November 30, 1847; 3.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Annual Meeting of the Board of Trustees, January 10, 1848; 4.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, March 15, 1848; 5.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, June 26, 1848; 6.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, October 1, 1848; 7.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, January 4, 1849; 8.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, January 23, 1849; 9.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Adjourned Meeting of the Board of Trustees, January 30, 1849; 10.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, June 22, 1849; 11.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, July 10, 1849; 12.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Adjourned Meeting of the Board of Trustees, July 17, 1849; 13.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Adjourned Meeting of the Board of Trustees, July 24, 1849; 14.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, August 28, 1849; 15.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, November 2, 1849; 16.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, November 14, 1849; 17.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, December 27, 1849; 18.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, January 27, 1851; 19.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Adjourned Meeting of the Board of Trustees, February 3, 1851; 20.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, March 27, 1851; 21.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, February 3, 1852; 22.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Adjourned Meeting of the Board of Trustees, February 9, 1852; 23.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Adjourned Meeting of the Board of Trustees, February 16, 1852; 24.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, August 27, 1852; 25.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, September 10, 1852; 26.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, December 18, 1852; 27.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, March 24, 1853; 28.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, April 29, 1853; 29.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, February 10, 1854; 30.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, Feburary 11, 1854; 31.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, February 14, 1854; 32.
- Western University of Pennsylvania, Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, April 1854-May 27, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, April 17, 1854; 1.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, May 27, 1854; 2.
- Western University of Pennsylvania, Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, May 30, 1854-August 1855 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Adjourned Meeting of the Board of Trustees, May 30, 1854; 1.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, June 9, 1854; 2.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, August 30, 1854; 3.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, January 10, 1855; 4.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, April 19, 1855; 5.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, May 1, 1855; 6.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, June 21, 1855; 7.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, June 27, 1855; 8.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, July 20, 1855; 9.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, August 22, 1855; 10.
- Western University of Pennsylvania, Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, Septemer 1855-February 1858 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, September 12, 1855; 1.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Adjourned Meeting of the Board of Trustees, September 18, 1855; 2.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, September 24, 1855; 3.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, January 9, 1856; 4.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, February 25, 1856; 5.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Monthly Meeting of the Board of Trustees, March 31, 1856; 6.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Monthly Meeting of the Board of Trustees, April 28, 1856; 7.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Monthly Meeting of the Board of Trustees, May 26, 1856; 8.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, June 30, 1856; 9.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, October 6, 1856; 10.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, October 20, 1856; 11.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, December 11, 1856; 12.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, December 19, 1856; 13.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, March 3, 1857; 14.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, May 4, 1857; 15.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, June 9, 1857; 16.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, July 24, 1857; 17.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, August 26, 1857; 18.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, February 5, 1858; 19.
- Western University of Pennsylvania, Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, Memorandum and Reports, May 1858-August 12, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Memorandum of the Board of Trustees, 1.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, May 18, 1858; 2.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees and Faculty Report, June 18, 1858; 3.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Adjourned Meeting of the Board of Trustees, July 13, 1858; 4.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Adjourned Meeting and Committee Report of the Board of Trustees, July 19, 1858; 5.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Adjourned Meeting of the Board of Trustees, August 3, 1858; 6.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, August 9, 1858; 7.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Adjourned Meeting and Committee Report of the Board of Trustees, August 12, 1858; 8.
- Western University of Pennsylvania, Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes and Committee Reports, August 25, 1858-November 1860 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting and Committee Report of the Board of Trustees, August 25, 1858; 1.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, September 20, 1858; 2.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, October 18, 1858; 3.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting and Committee Report of the Board of Trustees, November 3, 1858; 4.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting and Committee Report of the Board of Trustees, November 8, 1858; 5.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting and Committee Reports of the Board of Trustees, November 22, 1858; 6.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Adjourned Meeting of the Board of Trustees, December 6, 1858; 7.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, January 5, 1859; 8.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, February 11, 1859; 9.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting and Committee Report of the Board of Trustees, March 16, 1859; 10.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, June 8, 1859; 11.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, June 13, 1859; 12.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, October 6, 1859; 13.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, November 16, 1859; 14.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, January 27, 1860; 15.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Adjourned Meeting of the Board of Trustees, January 30, 1860; 16.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, June 15, 1860; 17.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, November 8, 1860; 18.
- Western University of Pennsylvania, Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, February 1861-November 1863 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, February 11, 1861; 1.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Adjourned Meeting of the Board of Trustees, February 25, 1861; 2.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Adjourned Meeting of the Board of Trustees, March 5, 1861; 3.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Adjourned Meeting of the Board of Trustees, March 14, 1861; 4.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, March 28, 1861; 5.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Adjourned Meeting of the Board of Trustees, April 4, 1861; 6.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Adjourned Meeting of the Board of Trustees, April 11, 1861; 7.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, September 13, 1861; 8.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, June 16, 1862; 9.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, November 25, 1863; 10.
- Western University of Pennsylvania, Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, January-October, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, January 13, 1863; 1.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, April 6, 1863; 2.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Adjourned Meeting of the Board of Trustees, April 13, 1863; 3.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees and Resignation Note from a Member, June 23, 1863; 4.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, July 6, 1863; 5.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Adjourned Meeting of the Board of Trustees, July 13, 1863; 6.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, September 3, 1863; 7.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, September 18, 1863; 8.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Quarterly Meeting of the Board of Trustees, October 5, 1863; 9.
- Western University of Pennsylvania, Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes and Faculty Report, January 1864-April 1866 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, January 11, 1864; 1.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, January 23, 1864; 2.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Special Meeting of the Board of Trustees, February 6, 1864; 3.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, April 4, 1864; 4.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees and Faculty Report, June 20, 1864; 5.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Quarterly Meeting of the Board of Trustees, October 3, 1864; 6.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, December 29, 1864; 7.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, March 13, 1865; 8.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, May 16, 1865; 9.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, June 26, 1865; 10.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, November 9, 1865; 11.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, November 24, 1865; 12.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, April 2, 1866; 13.
- Western University of Pennsylvania, Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, June-August 1866 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, June 25, 1866; 1.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, August 16, 1866; 2.
- Western University of Pennsylvania, Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, February 1867-January 1868 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, February 8, 1867; 1.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, April 1, 1867; 2.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, April 22, 1867; 3.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, June 24, 1867; 4.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, August 8, 1867; 5.
  - Western University of Pennsylvania, Meeting of the Board of Trustees, January 29, 1868; 6.
- Western University of Pennsylvania, Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes and Committee Report, April 1868-September 1870 (Box 1, Folder 19)